well welcome to all of you
we're gonna have a brief discussion
today with with Daniel Val and then we
you probably would have already seen by
the time you see this the webinar that
yeah the webinar he's gonna be
participating with Portugal so I
hopefully you all could listen to that
Daniel is one of the key persons at the
global level of fraternity development
his work on returns of cultural design
is fundamental for all of us and
actually makes it very clear to
understand what is required in a normal
process of transformation into a
regenerative world now under the current
pandemic things change very quickly
and Daniel has been at the forefront of
also in his homeland Majorca trying to
influence decision-making processes and
activities that will increase resilience
of the local communities so I welcome
you Danielle and the floor is yours
let's just chat a little bit yeah I mean
it's a it's a very different world like
no even the scenario planners and
futurists among us who like I remember
being in rooms with governments talking
about that global pandemics were the
high likelihood high global impact
scenarios of disruptive events of the
future I mean certainly the UK
government always had that on its radar
and and so many governments but somehow
we are so hypnotized by all sorts of
economic conversations that we even let
down the guard on watching out for
situations like this one like with Trump
firing his entire endemic swatch team
and now having two smaller that um but I
honestly feel a little bit silenced by
this conversation like they like what is
going on on the planet right now and I
find find it difficult to
to comment or give public talks or that
webinars right now I'm going to like
people will have watched by now this
this webinar that I had already promised
to control jest in Lisbon on
regenerative economies for regenerative
cultures but I feel like I prepared that
presentation in a pre pandemic world and
while a lot of the climate change in
global ecosystems collapse and planetary
emergency responses that you and I and
so many others have been talking about
working on for anything between 10 20 30
40 years and in some cases some of the
people we know in common all the things
that we've been saying we need to build
local resilience we need to engage
people in their region in a healing way
that they become guardians of the entire
local ecosystem that their economies
they're that circular by originally
focused economies in their very fabric
regenerative to restore the local
ecosystem to heal the local rivers and
the local forests in the local soil all
of that is now even more important all
the kind of wonderful academic
frameworks when I kind of went to town
and brought a 750 page PhD thesis on
designed for human and Planetary health
in 2006 and well that title in and of
itself
now rings with a very different
significance to a lot more people post
pandemic or in the middle of an
unfolding horrific pandemic that I think
most of us simply haven't because we
were bad an understanding economic
exponential growth that's why we despite
limits to growth and so many warnings
that this economic system is
structurally dysfunctional because it
has this inbuilt exponential necessity
for continued growth and we just felt
that we can continue to do so and now
we're seeing
fast forward in real time what an
exponential curve looks like when it
kills people in this economic
exponential curve has been killing
people for decades the strongest akin
economy on the planet has been built
around keep keeping a global war going
in the global self since the Second
World War
myth by mythology like the
methodologically subverting countries in
your region in particular one after the
other after the other to just create
wars in countries that could have never
been a threat to the United States but
it was their way of keeping an economy
going that is 50 percent dependent on
everything that is to do with the
military-industrial complex
and I feel like Ovid is showing us and
inviting us as when all sitting in our
confinement even that the linguistic
framing of social distancing we need to
socially connect now we need to maybe
physically distance ourselves to slow
the spread but we need to socially
connect and and and have the deeper
conversation about what's next and to me
that is also taking the time to look
into that what we had before was killing
more people every day when the virus is
killing right now it might still get
worse with the virus who knows but I
feel in my own personal and I think is
it that's what that's why I find it
difficult to really speak being it
because he can learn so much more just
listening to yourself and looking at
your own patterns in a situation like
this and what I've learned in the last
couple of weeks when I see these
horrific images of of people were trying
to help beyond I pushed beyond their
capacities people that have for for 48
hours 78 hundreds of hours
hardly slept and tried to help people
and they keep dying and new ones keep
coming in and and they have to make
decisions about this one we can still
say this person is young this person is
over 70 we don't have a incubator for
this person anymore and this is
happening life in Italy and it's
happening life in Madrid not far from
here and it's going to happen it's
happening in New York already and for me
on the one hand to really feel touched
by it by the horror of that and then
suddenly to realize that every day 5,000
children die of lack of access to clean
drinking water and I personally have
grown numb or had grown numb to that
daily horror to a point where I somehow
accepted it I find that is even far more
shocking to me at the moment and I feel
like this is the invitation to really
dig deep and understand that the system
we now all want to bounce back the
business as usual that we want to get
back to as quickly as possible was
murderous beyond belief to people in
Planet and it's not a place to go back
to her um but I also don't feel like I
apart from what we've been talking on
for a long long time which is bringing
the connection between people in place
into a healing union again people
understanding themselves of belonging to
a place and belonging to a region and
Riaan habit in it in a truly supportive
way understanding that the land provides
for us and therefore we provide for the
land and life provides for us and
therefore we provide for life it's
ancient wisdom that so many cultures
have tried to hand down from one
generation to the next and we've just
grown deaf too for too long
and that's what it's all about again and
and and it makes me even question do I
need to still sit and from my computer
and have these conversations or should I
just get my hands back into the soil and
probably a bit of both for all of us now
and that's what I'm doing I'm locked in
a flat but I'm planting some things on
my Terrace to keep myself saying I think
there are a few differences from this
pandemic to what we had been
experiencing in planetary collapse over
the last decades one is it's one agent
and that fits with the reductionist
mindset of the Western system so
identifying it's like the ozone hole and
the atmosphere it was three four
chemicals so it was something tackle
poverty and global change climate change
all these issues are complex and we
don't have the framework behind for
complex dealing with complex issues we
really need holistic approaches I think
that's one of the big challenges we have
and I think the second difference is
this has affected people like Tom Hanks
so we see 20 million children dying in
Africa right now as you mentioned and
nobody gets moved because it's far it's
it doesn't doesn't really touch me but
when you see people from all different
sectors and even the rich people getting
affected that is where people are
starting to react and say oh this this
can hit me
and yet we actually I think it's a
normal physiological thing that we turn
on to these things if I would be
thinking of the 27 million children I
and I see these images all the time on
on the networks of these children that
are just boning and skin that even if
you bring them food back there already
underdeveloped in their brain capacity
so they will never be functional totally
many of them because of their
undernutrition lasting so long
that if we didn't turn them would go
crazy now the thing is how how do we
avoid or how can we stimulate moving
into this new paradigm and avoid hopping
back into the old system as soon as the
quarantine is lifted and everybody wants
to go out and shop again I see here a
lot of discussion now very strong and
all over Latin America actually between
those that say the economy is more
important than a few people dying and we
see that more and more and I didn't
expect to hear it from some my friends
on Facebook which I basically have just
started unfriending a lot of people
because I just don't want to deal with
that sort of information coming to my
computer every day so how do we move
forward from your regenitive cultural
design experience how can we actually
manage to get to that three and a half
percent or ten percent whatever it is
that's required to create an avalanche
of change into a new paradigm having
people gone through this experience I I
don't think I know one answer to that
but what I do know is that that what you
just said raises the question for me of
he said if we let all that in we'd go
crazy my question would be haven't we
gone crazy already that we've grown numb
to that and really right yeah and and
and so I in that sense I think not so
much has changed we needed to
drastically build community resilience
for food sovereignty energy sovereignty
water sovereignty education basic needs
of people in place in ways
that ideally would be oriented in such a
way that they actually heal local
ecosystems that they reconnect local
communities with each other that they
wherever possible connect spare capacity
and unmet needs at the bio regional
scale to create really vibrant
mechanisms of providing for each other
and for that place so that place can
provide for us in the long term and and
there and we and this is also a
technological why is use of technology
of understanding what technologies to
use and what not to use and I think
what's important and what this has
driven us much more the crisis is that
we have at a crossroads between being
informed by a deeper ethic like I know
you you know we're both involved with
the earth charter I think this would be
the moment to really bring out the Earth
Charter again and say we actually have a
base line of an ethics document that we
aspire to live by as a human species mmm
because it's precisely like for me
that's the hopeful fact is that then
almost all around the world
the initial response to this of
governments was to protect the elderly
and the weak and not to protect the
economy I mean this they had a bit of a
slow response in making that ethical
choice but they made the ethical choice
we we are driving the economies against
the wall fast something that that we
thought when that we had asked to do
because we'd said this economy is is
destructive and deadly but they said no
that's impossible
with regard to the diffuse threat of
climate change that was already killing
more people and will kill many more
people if we don't do anything about it
but now the initial response was an
ethical one and and I think that that's
also something to be hopeful about but
now we are at this crossroads of saying
my people are celebrating the Chinese
response and suddenly that all these
voices of our how good if you just have
everybody connected
to AI completely and utterly observable
through their smartphones 24/7 with
ideally their body functions measured
through implants and we can just switch
on and switch off citizens when they
become not desirable anymore remotely
yeah and then that's a wonderful step
because we can respond to things like
epidemics very rapidly yeah it's not a
world I want to live in and it's if me
don't speak up that's the only reason
why I'm not keeping my mouth shut in
this situation because I'm really
worried I was just saying something
stupid at this point because most people
I listen to out there saying stupid
things because we don't know what this
is going to bring but I've made the
decision to not completely shut up and
sit and listen because of now my clients
little announcement of one child for
Colonia Corona capitalism and the
reminder that there are lots of people
out there who will use this crisis also
to erode civil liberties even more and
to implement control from top down even
more and if we don't also have the
deeper conversation at this point we
might wake up coming out of our
lockdowns
into a different world if we we need to
ask these civil liberties to be held
high and and so yeah for me that's why
we need global solidarity and we need to
address the issue that as we re
regionalize we have to watch out for the
people who are weary generalizing next
to us shoulder to shoulder because some
of them are xenophobic Nazis and they're
not save the planet and save humanity
people at this point there's a lot of
riri generalizing pulling back America
first this bioregion first this little
neighborhood first and of course we need
to meet our needs first but in a much
wiser like the way that the indigenous
people say wise decisions have to serve
yourself they have to serve your
community and they have to serve the
planet they have to serve at all three
levels and and as what I'm concerned
about is that there will be a push
towards more regional structures the
virus is forcing them upon us now but in
hungry that is turning into eroding
democracy and creating another fascist
dictatorship and and that can happen in
so many other places so so for me we
need global solidarity and local action
we need to not make the mistake that yes
we don't know how long we're all under
lockdown but I think we can't afford to
look back in four months time saying
well had I known that we're gonna be
under lockdown for four months and that
in that time the global economic system
was going to meltdown and everything
would change well I had acted I would
have acted differently in week two three
four or five or seven of lockdown I
think it's wiser to assume that we're in
this for at least three to six most
likely six to 12 or 18 months in
different facets and I don't want the
global system to completely melt down
because that would be quite difficult to
even find the energy to build a response
from so let's not call for that because
that it's difficult but but we need to
still in collaboration with all the
people who are now willing to be like to
collaborate who will even have the time
to listen who didn't before to say hey
there are certain sensible things to do
right now and they are about real
localizing production and consumption
and building renewable energy capacity
and sorting out the way we treat water
at the local scale in order to give um
good sanitation and clean drinking water
to people everywhere
locally and regionally these are the
basic things and that's where the SDGs
are not that out of a compound they're
like all the goals that we wanted to
implement bar number eight we we now
have a wonderful opportunity to make it
qualitative growth at the regional scale
rather than exponential economic growth
and and continued madness yeah it's very
interesting because we started the
regenerate Costa Rica initiative back in
mid July 2018 and it has been always a
difficult situation to deal with the
decision-makers in this country because
most of them are trained or at the
Kennedy School or Chicago with with
exactly that neoliberal market
philosophy we just had a discussion on
networks about the avocado and basically
the avocado is consumed by the middle
upper classes of Costa Rica this is it's
an expensive product and a few years ago
the government shut down importation
from Mexico because of health issues
with avocado and there has been a
tremendous movement on on internet
criticizing the government and actually
with legal processes to open up the
marketing and very influential people in
the decision-making process saying that
this government is totally wrong because
it's protective and we should open the
economy even more and if avocados is
cheaper in Mexico why do they have to
pay a high price and and these are
people that go in with 40 $50,000 cars
to a supermarket to buy and my reaction
was well you know that the avocado
Mexico is produced mostly Michoacan by
destroying native forests
they're killing campesino indigenous
leaders that are trying to predict the
land and it's it's the the drug industry
which has taken over there as a laundry
machine they don't have to be
competitive we cannot compete it's not a
free
market its it's a biased market because
they're not even paying for it for you
know it's just a laundry process so of
course they can sell it cheap or or
chilly then the other one of these
person said well I also think Chile has
good avocado and yeah and they've
destroyed their ecosystems they're right
now without water if the cost of the
destroying the ecosystem would have been
built into their avocados they'd be a
lot higher in price so we have the
political tendency to go against the
local production the bioregional
approaches actually our first female
president when she not great at Walmart
in the countries he said finally Costa
Rica stepped into development that is
the mentality that's behind many Latin
American countries at the moment pushed
by educational institutions that are a
big cause of the situation we're in now
because they taught us to compete they
taught us to destroy our competition
they they taught us to to open up to
these big market economies that the
trickle down effect which never happened
so I think this this pandemic now is a
tremendous opportunity I wish it would
have come in two or three years where we
would have had these seven bioregions
that we're working on already set up I
mean we've been working on local
currencies with farmers to enable them
to survive yeah all of those I mean I
think there's a lot of us who say I wish
we would have had a little longer and to
prepare a little more of course these
like even though they're the work that
the regenerative communities network and
all the bio regions and in that kind of
wider global alliance are doing
had it been a few more years along the
lines than we would have a real test
case of saying how can these structures
buffer such global collapses and global
changes and actually come out better
because they've already thought about
how to build that ecosystem of
regenerative enterprises that
doesn't maximize profit but maximizes
the win-win-win effects across all
aspects of of the region and and does so
in global solidarity with other regions
I think that yeah but but that's that's
really we've got we were having to serve
the wave and it's much bigger than we
all expected it to be quite so quickly
and it's still building right now so
buddy are you positive about
regenerative yoga now I'm positive that
that impulse of regeneration is aligned
with life's way of creating conditions
conducive to life and whether you make
it or not aligning yourself with that
impulse which is to me to my mind the
evolutionary impulse of what our second
identity not at what Miller and Daniel
are but our second identity as being
part of this planetary process that is
life wanting to continue I'm positive
that aligning myself with that is
meaningful whether what I see at the end
of my life seems like it was worth it
for me and and at the same time I still
think it is meaningful for me in my life
to now reconnect to place and reconnect
to my community
and continue to do what I can to
facilitate that global solidarity of
people who are wanting to do this
healing work everywhere I can't give
guarantees but I never said we anybody
could and I think anybody who pretends
is is kind of over stating the point and
possibly on an ego trip we don't know
and so I I don't know whether to be
positive but I'm positive that it's the
most
sensible thing to do from where I stand
that connecting with life's impulse to
create plenty of life connecting with
regenerating my community's capacity to
meet an uncertain future and to heal the
local ecosystems in ways that might my
daughter might have a richer rather than
a pure world to live in and is what I've
always been committed to and now I'm
even more committed to it and and the
urgency like I think that change is now
definitely no longer something that we
need to ask for like an aura Bateson has
if there's wonderfully like that
the notion of being a change maker has
just kind of been made obsolete change
made itself
now we just need to respond to this
change wisely and and yeah it's it's
weird because I keep saying the right
response is to shut up and listen and
yeah I am babbling on about it and so
but I try to do a lot of listening at
the moment because I think that's that's
where the wisdom is in in letting it in
even more so I'd like to I like to bring
up one last topic before we we had this
conversation over the years I've had a
lot to do with young people in many
different countries and first thing I
always do when I talk with with an
audience of students I asked who wants
to be a politician and they all go oh my
god no that no no then I tell them I
look if you leave politics to older
white-haired people like me you don't
have a future and then I came to to at
the beginning I could actually not
really move them but then I came to the
conclusion that if I give them hope and
I say we being told that we have to
adapt to a changing planet adaptation
will be important and I say that's the
biggest lie there is we have to build
the future we want not adapt to a coming
future which doesn't look
and we can and that hope actually
engages youth to want to do things to
want to learn to want to participate it
triggers them from totally I'm not doing
anything I'm just here with my Instagram
to I want to be involved and I think
that is a true potential to achieve this
change we need
and I I even see it with a even younger
generations the Millennials are still
there in between but the younger kids
they want to build their future and
they're excited about hey thank you for
saying that and because that is
important like is at the core of
designing regenerative cultures that
were designing and it is that design
impulse is giving the agency back to
each and every one of us to understand
that we can't but co-create the future
that all our actions and all our in
actions what we do and what we fail to
do create the future and that yes I mean
people like like William William Blake
said this two hundred fifty years ago
you must create the system or be
enslaved by another man's and so
basically we need to be vigilant to what
the world is people people are accepting
far too many structures rather than
taking agency in transforming them and I
like well particularly the politics
issues I was probably blind to that I
always thought politics was was a sort
of arena for people where there's a
slight ego issue but one of my great
mentors David all has just recently last
couple of weeks published a book called
democracy Unchained which is an edited
book of a great number of people in the
environmental and political movements in
the u.s. really pointing the finger at
themselves and saying that is the
greatest omission that our movement has
done that we created NGOs we lobbied
issues and stuff but we didn't
we create political parties and and
enter in the political process and in
the meantime a lot of people rig it
particularly in the US the political
game and and by the time we walk up to
it while suddenly everybody was
listening to the issues we've been
trying to champion the system was in
place that we could they did we couldn't
do anything and were like there isn't a
democracy in the US right now huh and
and that's what what what David is
trying to shine the light on so yeah I
think that but that's again back at the
local and regional scale regionalization
we need to become politically active and
engage with with all sectors and the
political the business sector like
that's the beauty of this situation
right now that that everybody is
completely stumped out of business as
usual even the successful players that
previously always had their don't waste
my time
I'm on a run here I'm super successful
and why should I change anything and now
not as successful anymore so they all
invited to really rethink things I mean
I live on an island where 80% of our
economy was dependent on tourism
I mean who on earth gives any credit to
somebody who's saying you're here by
these by the summer the hotels will be
full again anybody who says that now
it's just idiotic and people are very
quickly realizing that that's the case
and this year there won't be any tourism
and that after this even like everybody
doesn't like so many people won't have
the money anymore to travel plus so many
people will be scared to travel because
the virus still be out there and and so
the entire travel industry has just
imploded bit of a waste of my energy for
the last six months trying to like the
whole well look at the cruise ship
industry that's a that's the one that
has imploded
totally I don't think cruise cruise ship
industry will survive
I mean that's the one champagne cook
that I'm willing to pop and that would
be needed to implode and stay imploded
anyway yeah I just - all those like on
your course that they're listening to
this conversation I just really I think
it's for both of us also to remind each
other
um the whole mindset of how do we do
this quickly how do we take this to
scale all those kind of conversations
they're there they're part of the
problem as well because the way that a
wonderful conversation with Bill Reid
from Regenesis in January where he said
then really cannot save the planet but
he can save places and if we all do that
if we all save our place in deep
connection to our place and to our
community and our bio cultural
uniqueness of that region then all of us
doing it everywhere in global solidarity
will save the planet but it's not each
and every one of us who's gonna save the
planet and we're not taking anything to
scale we're not scaling up we're scaling
out or we with scaling down into like
what really matters and reconnection and
for me that that is really the deep
invitation and to just like really sit
and listen and and also as this is
getting worse let the emotions come up
and then have enough of a zooming out to
say okay if I'm so touched by what is
now going on through cope with 19 and
how many people are suffering
how does this relate to all the
suffering that there was that I was just
simply blind to prior to corporate 19 I
think that's a really important jump and
to understand that that this is the
first of many pandemics if we don't heal
the ecosystems because of course
weakened ecosystems and biodiversity
loss create the perfect conditions for
these kind of pandemics to spread and
for viruses to jump and so so they this
is all connected and we I think we need
to make that connection but Bob right
now I think really listening is the most
important thing yeah the final come the
regenerative communities Network mission
is exactly that established learning
sites across the planet that are
actually already doing some sort of
regeneration and co-creating solutions
at the local level and having a global
impact through the whole network Daniel
thank you so much because I've had we've
been having conversations all together
for a long time to create that Network
like yeah you say all like I love what
Stuart Cohen is doing and John Fullerton
is doing and I love what cake rebirth is
doing and we're all doing our bit Joe
Blow is doing his bit in his way and so
many so many people are out there really
trying to serve and I think we all have
our strengths and weaknesses but but
that's part of life that's like that
diversity can also be our strengths if
we keep em keeping the
hyah mission of being of service to life
and also yeah my current role has been
over the last couple years like getting
a big needle and thread and bringing all
these groups together to collaborate in
a more unified way and that's where we
generate Costa Rica comes to life
because I can bring in all these Kate is
gonna support us with the doughnut
economic analysis communities network
it's gonna support us with all this
exchange savory Institute is already
helping us to transform all cattle into
and to regenitive holistic cattle
grazing so bringing all these networks
together to work in a territory and work
in other characters as we go along in
the majority of communities network I
think is that the best possibility to
actually stop saying we need to
collaborate and start saying we are
collaborating and I know you're dealing
or leading an initiative or regeneration
in in majorca and I think whatever you
do even if it's big or small is a
learning process for other areas that
can then start thinking in terms of
regeneration I really appreciate your
time
I know you're fully booked and I hope we
have a another chance in the future to
keep on this conversation it's been very
rich we will hopefully be able to have
the link to your next webinar with
Portugal and I think this has been a
very eye-opening opportunity especially
seeing your emotional involvement it's
not just an academic poster it's a human
poster behind this and and thank you for
that venue No thank you that for me this
is really important that we actually
allow our feelings and our multiple ways
of knowing into this and they I mean
people might not get this from my
writing because my writing is maybe
influenced through my academic
to the point that sometimes doses seems
very kind of male and academic and so on
but but actually I think this is exactly
the bridge we need to make to really
trust our intuitions and our emotions in
this context informed by good systems
analysis and systemic lateral thinking
and all those kind of things but but if
we if we only covered it too much from
kind of a project management line and
without the heart and then I don't think
it's truly regenerative and also if even
even within the regenerative movement we
should rigid rigidify what it means
because it's for me ultimately it's the
evolutionary impulse of life creating
conditions conducive to life to keep
responding to keep learning to keep
putting us in the wider context of the
whole we are in that we're trying to
serve and that's a big umbrella and that
holds a lot of different perspectives
but that's our strength not a weakness
um that's the best closing thank you
thank you thank you